French Literature mss., LMC 1391 LMC 1391
Lilly Library
- French Literature mss.
  - L'Eternel fatigué… sur la terre. A.D., undated.; 1 p. 16 cm.
    Brief tract of 18 liines in which Mirabaud [i.e., Paul Henri Thiry, baron d'holbach] is mentioned and in which Mirabeau may be vilified.
    Signed with indecipherable initials.
    Seven words on verso: …nullam de eo…
    Removed from Vie publique et privée de Honoré Gabriel Riquetti, comte de Mirabeau. Paris: Hotel d'Aiguillon, 1791 (Lilly DC147 .M7 V656). 1977
  - Farrèré, Claude, 1876-1957, author. L'Extravagante Aventure D'Arif Pacha. A.D., undated.; 11 leaves 31-33 cm.
    In black ink with correctionis.
    Portions blacked out.
    Paper watermarked Original Turkey Mill Kent.
    In rose, green and gold slip case.
  - Farrèré, Claude, 1876-1957, author. Opium, translated by Montgomery Evans. T.D.S., undated.; 202 [i.e. 200] p. 27 cm.
    Carries a few holograph corrections.
    Errors in paging: 87 numbered 88, 115 numbered 116.
    Translation of Claude Farrèré's Fumé d'opium, first published in Paris in 1904.
    Preface by Pierre Louÿs.
    Gift. 1957
  - Fleury, Jules, 1821-1889, author. To Mon cher maitre. Asks to send him new books and a copy of Etudes de l'antiquité en le moyen âge; wishes to see him in the near future but he is never there and the trip would be too hard. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Letter signed: Champfleury.
    Removed from Jules Fleury, Les bourgeois de Molinchart, Paris: Locard-Davi et de Vresse, 1855 (Lilly PQ2252 .B772). 1977
  - Fromentin, Eugène, 1820-1876, novelist, art critic. St. Maurice, La Rochelle, France. To [?]. Will be vacationing until November and won't be able to attend fine arts jury meeting. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 20 cm.
    Dated: "vendredi, 12 Octobre," n.y.
    Embossed letterhead: M F.
    Removed from Fromentin, Un été dans le Sahara. Paris: M. Levy frères, 1857 (Lilly DT333 .F931). 1980
  - Gault, Jean- Louis, 1952-, poet. Souviens-toi de la colline… [first words of poem]. A.D.S., undated.; 1 leaf 14 cm.
    Poem of 13 lines in black ink.
    Removed from Jean-Louis Gault, L'enfant-fleur, Paris: Éditions Saint-Germain-des-Prés, 1974 (Lilly PQ2667 .A9366 E56), no. 31 of 40 numbered copies. 1977
  - Genet, Jean, 1910-1986, author. One leaf from the manuscript of Haute Surveillance, beginning "Si monsieur. Elle sera pour moi…" A.D., undated.; 1 leaf 25 cm.
    Verso of manuscript carries a marked-out version beginning "Elle sera pour moi…"
    Published in Genet, Haute Surveillance, Paris, Jean Belmont, 1947, on p. 95-96.
    Removed from the above title (Lilly PQ2613 .E46H37). 1974
  - Genlis, Stéphanie Félicité Ducrest de Saint Aubin, comtesse de, 1746-1830, author. "pour la première fois depuis qu'elle était instruite de son malheur pauline…" [first line of incomplete story of Pauline and Marval]. A.D.S., undated.; 2 p. 22.5 cm.
    Page 16 and 17 of story.
    Last line of page 16 bears the date 30 Mars 1814 as a part of the story.
    Purchase. 1977.
  - Glatigny, Joseph Albert, 1839-1873, poet. Hotel de France, Menton. To François Coppée. Glatigny refers to Le Passant Mme Cruvilli, and his travels from Nice to Menton to Monaco. A.L.S., undated.; 2 leaves 21 cm.
  - Goncourt, Jules Alfred Huot de, 1830-1870, author. To Cher Monsieur. Mentions "L'élevation de votre chronique" and comments "Le: Blagueur." A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 20.5 cm.
    Dated: Mercredi.
    In pencil at bottom of letter: Homme de Lettres.
    Removed from Edmond & Jules de Goncourt, Manette Salomon. Paris, Librairie Internationale… 1867 (Lilly PQ2261 .M275 copy 2). 1984
  - Gourmont, Remy de, 1858-1915, critic. Aprés avoir raconté l'histoire du Parnasse, M. Ricard nous donne une curieuse étude anecodotique sur Verlaine. [first three lines of article.] A.D., undated.; 4 p. 21.5 cm.
    Review of Ricard's study of Verlaine with corrections.
    Newspaper clippings of an article pasted on the last page.
    At the head of the first page: Les Journaux.
    Removed from Remy de Gourmont, Promenades littéraires, Paris: Société du Mercure de France, 1904-1927 (Lilly PQ2266 .P965). 1977
  - Gourmont, Remy de, 1858-1915, critic. Guillaume de Machaut et son amie. A.D.S., undated.; 9 p. 18 cm.
    Published as Part I of Le Roman de Guillaume de Machaut et de Peronne D'Armentières in Gourmont, Promenades littéraires, vol.5, 1923, pages 5-14.
  - Gourmont, Remy de, 1858-1915, critic. Le livre de Victor Hugo est également, pour d'autres motifs, un de ceux qu'on ne peut examiner ce quelques lignes [first two lines of article]… Ce livre est une tristesse. A.D.S., undated.; 2 p. 22 cm.
  - Gourmont, Remy de, 1858-1915, critic. Notre époque. Sémantique humaine. A.D.S., undated.; 5 p. 13-24 cm.
    Article on the changes of meaning of words and how names of objects come into existence.
    Upper right hand corner cut from first page; third page cut to 13 cm. with missing portion pasted to top of fourth page.
  - Gourmont, Remy de, 1858-1915, critic. To Cher Monsieur. Writes about getting a good reproduction of an etching and mentions his article on Verhaeren. A.L.S., undated.; 2 p. 16 cm.
  - Gozlan, Léon, 1803-1866, novelist. Passage Sauluier 7. To "cher ami et cher confrère." Requests a note stating when he prefers Gozlan's Les nuits de Père La Chaise be published. Has already told him why he has decided to teach for a living. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Gozlan, Les emotions de Polydore Marasquin. Paris: M. Levy Frères, 1857 (Lilly PQ2268 .E54). 1980
  - Grandclaude, Maurice, 1887-, author. To "Mon cher ami." 2 A.L.S., undated.; 6 p. 17 cm.
    Removed from Maurice Grandclaude's Étude Critique sur les Livres des Assises de Jérusalem. Paris, Jouve, 1923 (D183 .G7). 1951
  - Guérin, Charles, 1873-1907, poet. [Poetry fragments]. A.Ds., undated.; 2 p. 13.5 cm.
    Contents: 1) On ne compterai… first words of six lines of poetry in ink with pencilled notes crossed out. 2) Se sentir chaque soir plus paisible-first words of six lines of poetry with pencilled notes crossed out.
    Accompanied by …les cendres ameres d'une âme qui s'est comsumée elle-meme. Quote from Shelley's Prometheus Unbound in unknown hand in ink and English translation in pencil A.D. 1 p. 9.5 cm.
    Removed from Charles Guérin, Joies grises, Paris: Paul Ollendorff, 1894 (Lilly PQ2613 .U2J7 1894). 1977
  - Heredia, José Maria de, 1842-1905, poet. Le re'veil d'un Dieu. A.D.S., undated.; 1 leaf 25 cm.
    Four stanzas of 4, 4, 3, 3 lines.
    Dedicated to Marcel Fouquier.
    Paper watermarked Imperial Treasury De La Rue.
    Removed from Heredia, Les Trophees, Paris, Alphonse Lemerre, 1893. 1972
  - Heredia, José Maria de, 1842-1905, poet. Redondillas. A.D.S., undated.; 2 leaves 18 cm.
    Eight stanzas of four lines each.
    Lined paper.
  - Heredia, José Maria de, 1842-1905, poet. To "cher ami". "C'est un vrai guignon, cher ami". He is concerned about missing a dinner invitation and promises to meet again on Saturday. A.L.S., undated.; 2 leaves 18 cm.
    Paper watermarked Treasury.
  - Hugo, Victor Marie, comte, 1802-1885, novelist. Note of congratulation concerning the facsimile of a Hugo letter and an engraving of John Brown by Paul Chenay. A.N.S., undated.; 2 p. 12.5 cm.
    Facsimile of the Hugo letter to Chenay, Jan. 21, 1861, and the John Brown engraving are bound in the volume from which the note was removed.
    Removed from Hugo, John Brown. Paris, E. Dentu, 1861 (Lilly PQ2304 .B87). 1980
  - Hugo, Victor Marie, comte, 1802-1885, novelist. To Henri Descamps, Rue Saint Honoré, En face le passage Delorme, Paris. A.L.S., undated.; 1 leaf 20 cm.
    Removed from Hugo, Les quatre vents de l'esprit … Paris, J. Hetzel, A. Quantin, 1881 (Lilly PQ2289 .A2). 1972
  - Hugo, Victor Marie, comte, 1802-1885. To Eugéne Renduel. Concerns an edition of his book. A.L.S., undated.; 3 p. 21 cm.
    Letter is dated Aug. 16, n.y.
    Removed from Hugo, Marion de Lorme. Paris, Eugéne Renduel, 1831 (Lilly PQ2285 .M5). 1974
  - Ibert, Jean-Claude, 1928-, poet. Prophème IX. A.D.S., undated.; 1 p. 20 cm.
    Poem of four lines in black ink.
    Published in Le Saut de l'Ange
    Drawing in black, green and red, signed by Ibert, on adjacent page.
    Removed from Ibert, Le Saut de l'Ange. Paris, Editions de Minuit, 1957 (Lilly PQ2669 .B25S26). 1985
  - Jammes, Francis, 1868-1938, poet, novelist. Feuilles dans le vent: proof sheet of "L'auberge des poètes." D., undated.; 1 p. 25 cm.
    Includes inscription stating that the page is ready to print after the few corrections are made and signed: F Jammes.
    Removed from Jammes, Feuilles dans le vent. Paris: Mercure de France, 1913 (Lilly PQ2619 .A5 F42 copy 1) 1981
  - Jandot, Jacques, poet. [Four poems]. A.D.s, undated.; 4 leaves 14 cm.
    Contents: 1) 4 heures, 10 lines; 2) Instantanée, 8 lines; 3) un coup de pied [first line], 8 lines; 4) Un tiroir ouvert, 8 lines. Published in Jacques Jandot, Instantanées.
    Removed from Jacques Jandot, Instantanées, [Paris]: Librairie Saint-Germain-des-Prés, 1974 (Lilly PQ2670 .A55 I58) no. 36 of 40 copies. 1977
  - Joubert, Jean, 1928-, poet. Usant d'abus, de meutes et d'abois,/ le temps chasseur surgit à flanc d'automne. [first two lines of poem]. A.D.S., undated.; 1 leaf 30 cm.
    Ten lines of poetry in ink.
    Removed from Jean Joubert, J'ai vu dans l'eau ta bouche mouillée de larmes, Paris: Éditions Saint Germain-des-Prés, 1973 (Lilly PQ2670 .O9 J25). 1977
  - Lacretelle, Jacques de, 1888-, novelist. 60 avenue de Lena, Paris. To Madame Marguerite (Eymery) Vallette. Thanks her for the good review of his book. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 27 cm.
    Pencilled note in upper right hand corner: à RACHILDE aprés son article dans le "Mercure de France" du 15 Oct. 1920.
    Removed from Jacques Lacretelle, Le vie inquiète de Jean Hermelin, Paris: Bernard Grasset, 1920 (Lilly PQ2623 .A216 V65). 1977
  - Langhenhoven, Jéhan Van, poet. fais provision/ en bâtis maisions/ avant que la mort/ ne te surprenne dans la sommeil des cargos. A.D.S., undated.; 1 leaf 14 cm.
    Published in Langhenhoven, Nuit dérivée 1974.
    Removed from Jéhan Van Langhenhoven, Nuit dérivée, Paris: Éditions Saint-Germain-des-Prés, 1974 (Lilly PQ2672 .A28 N96). 1977
  - La Tour du Pin, Brigitte (O'Connor) de, comtesse To Monsieur. Writes of receiving a letter from her son Patrice, a prisoner of war, and inquires whether he could accept letters from Patrice so that she could hear from him more than once a month. A. card, undated.; 5.5 cm.
    Written on calling card of Comtesse F. de Le Tour du Pin, dated Mar. 18.
    Removed from Patrice de La Tour du Pin, La quête de joie. Paris: la Tortue, 1933 (Lilly PQ2623 .A679 Q5). 1977
  - La Tour du Pin, Patrice de, 1911-, poet. Le Bignon-Mirabeau, Loiret, France. To Jacques Collin Delavaud. Le Virolau à Britantes, Indre. Writes about coming up to Paris the next day to have his teeth fixed. Mentions that "Mon vieux Bignon n'a pas trop changé,…" A. Pc.S., undated.; 1 p. 11 cm.
    Source unknown. 1977
  - Maeterlinck, Maurice, 1862-1949, dramatist. To Adolphe van Bever. Presents a copy of "Le Trésor des Humbles" and mentions the review "L'Aube". A.L.S., undated.; 2 p. 9 cm.
    Bever founded L'Aube in 1895 with Pierre Guédy according to Paul Leautand in Adolphe Van Bever, Les Amis D'Edouard, No. 114 1927, (Lilly PQ2623 .E14 A75) on page 15.
    Mounted in Maeterlinck, Le Trésor des Humbles, Paris: Société du Mercure de France, 1896 (Lilly PQ2625 .A5 T79) which is also inscribed by Maeterlinck, to Van Bever. 1985
  - Maupassant, Guy de, 1850-1893, author. Cannes, 1 rue de Redan. To "Mon cher ami". "Je n'ai pas reçu les 2 derniers nuneros de la Vie Militaire. Pour-quoi? Ou sont-ils? Ou voyagent-ils?" A.L.S., undated.; 2 p. 15 cm.
    Dated 8 Avril, n.y.
    Removed from Maupassant, La Maison Tellier, Paris, Victor Havard, 1881 (Lilly PQ2349 .M232). 1975
  - Mérimée, Prosper, 1803-1870, novelist. To "mon cher ami". Mentions the July Revolution, P. Lacordaire and Dr. Maure. A.L.S., undated.; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Prosper Mérimée, Carmen, Paris, Michel Lévy frères, 1826 (Lilly PQ2362 .C2 1846). 1973
  - Miguel, André, 1920-, poet. Boule Androgyne. A.D.S., undated.; 106 leaves 30 cm.
    In ink with faces decorating some of the leaves
    Varies slightly from the published work with the last 17 of the poems in the published work not included in this manuscript.
    Published at Paris by Saint Germain-Des-Pres, 1973.
  - Miscellaneous notes removed from Victor Hugo, Le Rhin. Paris, Jules Renouard, 1845. D., undated.; 4 p. 10.5 x 21 cm.
    Notes in ink on two leaves in two or more hands with diagonal marks crossing out the notes.
    Removed from Victor Hugo, Le Rhin. Paris, Jules Renouard, 1845 (Lilly PQ2289 .R6 1845). 1980
  - Mouravit, Gustave, 1840-, bibliophile, author. Inscription to his father: "Offert in mémoire de mon père." A.N.S., undated.; 1 p. 23 cm.
    Inscribed in ink on paper cover of the author's Poetes & bibliophiles: les devises des vieux poetes… Paris: d. Morgand et C. Fatout, 1879 (Lilly PN6312 .M929). 1976
  - [Notes regarding Sophie Arnould by Jules and Edmond de Goncourt]. Ds., undated.; 8 p. 18-19 cm.
    In ink and pencil in two hands.
    One blank page.
    First set of notes, 6 p., concerns the plan of the 18th century house of opera singer Sophie Arnould.
    Second set of notes, 2 p., concerns the Charpentier 1885 edition of Sophie Arnould.
    Removed from Goncourt, Sophie Arnould Paris, E. Dentu, 1877 (Lilly PQ2661 .S712 1877). 1984
  - Pector, Désiré, author. Paris. To Madame Hervieu, Paris. Food ration cards. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 14 cm.
    Removed from Jean Psichari's La Croyante. Paris, Stock, 1899 (Author's presentations copy to Paul Hervieu) (PQ2631 .S53C9). 1958
  - Ponsard, François, 1814-1867, poet, playwright. To "Monsieur." A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 18.7 cm.
    Dated 7 Juin.
    Removed from Ponsard. L'Honneur et l'argent: Comédie en cinq actes et en vers. Paris. Lévy frères, 1853 (Lilly PQ2382 .P7 H77) 1994
  - Ramuz, Charles Ferdinand, 1878-1947, author. …il faisait trés froid, ce soir-là [first line of leaf 86 from Ramuz, La guerre dans le haut-pays] A.D.S., undated.; 1 leaf 21.5 cm.
    In black ink on gray paper.
    Removed from Ramuz, La guerre dans le haut-pays. Lausanne: C. Tarin, 1915 (Lilly PQ2635 .A35G94). 1977
  - Renan, Ernest, 1823-1892, philosopher. Note relative to Napoleon III and Karol Edmund Chojecki, and the dates 1860 and 1869. A.N.S., undated.; 1 p. 15.5 cm.
    In pencil.
    Removed from Ernest Renan, Heriette Renan. Paris: Imprimerie J. Claye, 1862 (Lilly PQ2386 .R37H52). 1978
  - Richepin, Jean, 1849-1926, writer. Fils de fille. A.D., undated.; 2 leaves 20 cm.
    Poem of 28 lines.
    Published in Jean Richepin, La chanson de gueux, Paris: Librarie Illustrée, 1876 (Lilly PQ2387 .R4 C5).
    Removed from Jean Richepin, La chanson de gueux, Paris: Librarie Illustrée, 1876 (Lilly PQ2387 .R4 C5). 1977
  - Romains, Jules, 1885-1972, novelist, poet. École Du Vieux Colombier, Paris 9, Rue Du Cherche-Midi. To Franz Hellens. Gives suggestions for an article and deals at length with "le symbolisme" and the younger generation of poets. A.L.S., undated.; 4 p. 21 cm.
  - Rousslot, Jean, 1915-, poet. Nue… [poem]. A.D.S., undated.; 2 leaves 18.5 cm.
    In red ink on conjugate leaves.
    Accompanied by engraving of figure in red and yellow signed by Roger Toulouse.
    Laid in Jean Rousselot, Hors d'eau. Paris: Saint Germain-des-Prés, 1968 (Lilly PQ2635 .O9618 H82). 1977
  - Sand, Gerorge, 1804-1876, author. To Monsieur. Wants him to return the corrected proof and manuscript. Mentions the arrangement of a book. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Letter embossed GS in upper left-hand corner.
    Accompanied by a translation.
  - Sarcey, Francisque, 1827-1899, critic. "à millegible Farrari son collaborateur". A.N.S., undated.; 1 p. 17.5 cm.
    Inscribed in Sarcey, Souvenirs D'Age Mur. Paul Ollendorff, 1892 (Lilly PQ2421 .S4Z48). 1981
  - Sarcey, Francisque, 1827-1899, critic. … En Hollande. A.D., undated.; 9 p. 20.5 cm.
    Title as given: Comment je deviens conférencier En Hollande.
    Page 7 in two parts.
    Varies slightly from published text of Chapter XIII, En Hollande, pages 224-239 only, of Souveniers D'Age Mur.
    Accompanied by two clippings picturing Sarcey.
    Removed from Sarcey, Souveniers D'Age Mur. Paris, Paul Ollendorff, 1892 (Lilly PQ2421 .S4Z48). 1981
  - Sarcey, Francisque, 1827-1899, critic. To Gustave Larroumet. Refers to "la dernier article". A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 17.5 cm.
    Letter addressed to: Mon cher directeur.
    Watermark: Verley, with two decorative devices.
    Bound in Sarcey, Souveniers D'Age Mur. Paris, Paul Ollendorff, 1892 (Lilly PQ2421 .S4Z48). 1981
  - Sue, Marie Joseph Eugene, 1804-1857, novelist. To Monsieurs U. Canel ou A. Guyot. He is writing about La Coucaratcha, the third volume of which should carry the words 2nd edition. A.L.S., undated.; 1 leaf 20 cm.
    La Coucaratcha was published in Paris by Canel and Guyot in 1832-1834.
    Attached address leaf.
  - Valéry, Paul Ambroise, 1871-1945, author. Montmirail, Marne. To Arthur Honegger, 21 Rue Duperré, Paris. He discusses Amphion, a telephone appointment, and asks "Savez vous si Ida [Rubinstein] est rentrée?" A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 27 cm.
    Amphion was composed in 1929 and first performed on June 23, 1931.
    Removed from Honegger, Amphion… Paris, Rouart, Lerolle & Cie, 1931 (Lilly M1510 .H772A5). 1975
  - Villain, Jean Claude, poet. O Jules marin/le flux refute/ sa loi sommaire, [first three lines of poem]. A.D.S., undated.; 1 leaf 14 cm.
    Removed from Jean Claude Villain, Au creux de l'oreille, Paris: Librairie Saint-Germain-des-Prés, 1974 (Lilly PQ2682 .I38 A88), no. 26 of 40 numberd copies. 1977
  - Vogüé, Eugène Marie, Melchior, vicomte de, 1848-1910, novelist, critic. Cercle de L'Union Artistique, 5, Rue Boissy D'Anglas, Paris. To "madame." Discusses his travel plans. Hopes they can visit the Carthusian monastery in Villeneuve together. A.L.S., undated.; [3] p. 17.5 cm.
    Removed from Vogüé, Le roman russe. Paris: Plon-Nourrit et Cie., 1910 (Lilly PG3095 .V8 1910). 1986
  - Dujardin, Edouard, 1861-1949, author. Four letters to James B. Pinker, literary agent, 1929, December 5-14 (Bound 1)
    Case includes sticker of Alexander Neubauer
  - Scheler, Lucien. Pare de bleu volubilis; poeme objet, 1986 (Foliobox 24)